A Guide to the Papers of Henry James, 1855-1969, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
  - Two Men: A Novel by Elizabeth Stoddard by Henry James 1865, AMs, 23 pp. on 23 l. (Box-folder 1:17)
    - Henry James to "Dearest Curtises Both" [Mr. and Mrs. Daniel Sargent Curtis], 1900 August 1, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 3:86)
      Hideous news from [Mouza?] which filled him with sickness. Stirred with pity and horror that they must be in. Makes one aware how their "lover," the blessed old Italy, is unique. All had sympathy for the honest man, Humberto, with his straight ways, and his handsome public purposes and the hideous brutish villainy. What grief for his family and for Venice. Record heat in London. The Chinese nightmare has darkened all things. #6251-ag
    - Henry James to Hans [Hendrik Christian Anderson], 1900 September 7, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:87)
      Distressed by his letter. Worried when he hadn't heard. Sent emissary to him: his cousin, a painter, to see what happened. Feels he had a devil of a time; didn't say what was the matter or what the operation was for. Glad he is on his feet again. Stick to Newport and his family, until he can go it alone, and then come to James and he will give him a further lift. Family duties and anxieties have been heavy on James. His little house is constantly occupied. If he gets over will be delighted to see him. Get well and keep up his heart. #6251
    - Henry James to A. Llewellyn Roberts, 1900 October 1, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 4:1)
      Desires to support the application for assistance made on behalf of Mrs. Stephen Crane to the Royal Library Fund and testify to Mrs. Crane's extreme need of such aid. #6251-at
    - Henry James to [William Morton?] Fullerton, 1900 October 2, ALS, 6 pp. on 3 l. (Box-folder 4:2)
      How can he thank him for letter? Read into his hurried words everything. Understands his practical impossibilities. Forgive gruesome image of his description of feelings. The grey years gather; he feels his loss and gain if he had been free. Saw Paris of these months as a positive hell of worry and oppression for him. Rejoices he had three weeks in May. Asks him to put his record and impressions in order so he may have cognition of them. His letter exhales complexity and obscurity of trouble and he may hold out assurance of help. Thinks the part from which he sets out is that of essential loneliness of his life: it is the deepest thing about him. #6251-m
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Humphrey] Ward, 1900 October 14, ALS, 10 pp. on 5 l. (Box-folder 4:3)
      Infinitely touched by kindness and sympathy of her letter and interested in her news. He has been out of the current for a long time, and feels as if his oldest friend would have been excusable to exclude him from all earthly affairs. It's humane of her to give him another chance. Kind of her to ask after his brother who has been little with him this summer as he has been at Nanheim cures, etc. He is better and has been able to write most of his first course of Gifford lectures. The second course he has had to renounce. His sister-in-law was with him much of the latter half of the summer. She abandoned the idea of returning to the United States for two months to see her other children. His summer has been a deluge of family, and he has not stirred from home. How rich her existence, how numerous her contacts, how perfect her machinery. He should have sent her his lately published tales, except he thought she was given over to last work on Eleanor. Shall have book sent now. It represents all tales he has finished and issued. He niggles away at dictation and finds his blessed little place promoted continuity. He has done another book of short stories, and a shortish novel to appear in the spring, and immersed in a third which is to "serialized" in Harper's fills all his consciousness. Congratulates her on the consummation of Eleanor: infinitely awaits the volume. Delightful for her to have the pretext for another month in Rome! Impossible for him to join his brother there as he proposes. He will go to town January 1 until May, and will see her and let her tell him all about the play. Rejoices for her in an associate as charming and literary, etc. as Julian S. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. Curtis, 1900 October 22, ALS, 6 pp. on 3 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 4:4)
      The Soft Side was doubly due to them, for they gave him in three vivid words the subject of The Tree of Knowledge, about Gordon G. and his father and mother. He is starved of Italy, but doesn't like Rome as it is today: an eternal dodging of impossible people, and a place of terror before May 1. Has met Lady Radnor. Talks much about Barbaro. Has only one lovely emotion left: a passion for the Empress Dowager, although her dynasty does sound like a Chinese sneeze! He is convinced he should have been a Mandarin. #6251-ag
    - Henry James to Mr. Robinson, 1900 November 3, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 4:5)
      Rejoices Mrs. Robinson is able to come, and expects both Thursday. Foresees they will be full of assistance. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Hans [Hendrik Christian Anderson], 1900 November 3, 8 pp. on 2 l (Box-folder 4:6)
      Rejoices in news he will come straight down and stay many days before his feverish impatience to get to Rome, work, and glory. Congratulates him on that liberation. His recent purgatory will have been worthwhile. Tells him where to go in London, how to visit his cousin, and how to get to Rye. Rejoices he is found and strong. #6251
    - Henry James to Mr. Robinson, 1900 November 11, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 4:7)
      Obliged for letter and inspiring sketch. All he suggests deserves much thinking. He has distilled the poison, and part of it will work. Difficulty is he must wait. Can't think of it until next year, when he shall know what money he can muster for gardening. His idea for terrace, etc. appeals strongly. Other idea for garden terrifies him: it may crowd him and make his little enclosure look smaller than it already it. Source of terror is question. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Humphrey] Ward, 1900 November 22, ALS, 8 pp. on 4 l. (Box-folder 4:8)
      Has had two impulses: to write to her soon as he heard of her father's death; and to let a little time pass. He had just begun Eleanor and was absorbing it. Writes about parental extinctions. When he finished book he had words to utter to heal wounds rather than to be harsh to them. Her father had the serenity of his accomplished age, after many mutations, and assuredly after seeing himself magnificently fulfilled by her. She can think of the pleasure and pride she must have filled his life with. Hopes he read Eleanor. He never met him, but was impressed with his published personal recollections, and what a date was his death in the Arnold family cycle! Thanks for her letter on The Soft Side, a little bundle of sordid potboilers which he is forced to write, because there is no demand for anything else so he has done another volume of similar snippets, even though he is old enough to know better. He reads as much fiction as he can read. Took liberty in inordinate degree with Eleanor. Many compliments on book, and feels it the highest tribute he can pay. He can't criticize though he could re-write! The thing is infinitely delightful and distinguished, and that's enough. Won't pretend book hasn't a weakness, a rather grave one, or she will doubt his intelligence. Goes into detail: Lucy vs. Eleanor, etc. He recognizes that not a solitary reader or critic will have made his criticism, and when a book is beautiful, nothing does matter. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Hans [Hendrik Christian Anderson], "Thursday" [1900 November 29], ALS, 3 pp. on 2 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 4:9)
      Just heard he has arrived. James is alone, and wants Hans to stay as long as possible. Gives train schedule. His room awaits for him. #6251
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Clement] Waters, 1900 December 1, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 4:10)
      Should have thanked her for information regarding Miss Robinson, but away. Glad she has her to watch over her, and that she has sought rest and protection from ferocious devotions. He is writing Miss Robinson preaching unqualified surrender. I am sure she will then come back with all the fruits of victory. #6251-d
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Clement] Waters, 1900 December 10, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 4:11)
      Kind to write again regarding their admirable, difficult friend. Relieved she is being nursed, tended, and kept quiet, but depressed regarding her reluctance to join her in the South. London from any point of view is not the place for her. Wishes some high medical voice would say three to four months abroad her absolute duty. #6251-d
    - Henry James to "Daniele Barbaro" [Daniel Sargent Curtis], 1900 December 21, ALS, 8 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 4:12)
      Going to Lamb House for Christmas and his next activities. Next year on excellent footing for going abroad to his beloved Italy. Talks of their site and Roman view and his own activities. Things are gloomy and the roar is anything but over. #9511-q
    - Henry James to Hans [Hendrik Christian Anderson], 1901 January 12, ALS, 8 pp. on 4 l. (Box-folder 4:13)
      Thinks of him on the banks of the Tiber, with joy and sympathy. How jolly to be restored to Rome and the old life, the old love, the pure independent passions of the mind and the imagination. Came to town for three months. Hopes the summer will bring him to England with a good bit of a fairy tale to tell him. #6251
    - Henry James to Violet Hunt, [1901 March 14], ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 4:14)
      He has already written his servants in the country to look up volume, and immediately send it to her. Can he come in and see her some day next week to express his contrition and explain his infirmity? #6251-o
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Humphrey] Ward, 1901 March 15, ALS, 12 pp. on 3 l. (Box-folder 4:15)
      Most kind her letter, etc. and it needs all his courage not to be responsive, but it is impossible for him to go abroad this spring. He is not free, as he is bound to an unfinished and belated book on his hands. Also his brother and his wife arrive from Italy at Easter to come down with him for a month. Talked with Mrs. Peter Harrison who knows her villa well, and she made his mouth water. Has liveliest appreciation of her remarks on The Sacred Fountain. Says the book isn't worth discussing. It was a remarkably accidental one, and the merest joux d'esprit. Started as a short story and never stopped. Tried to make it a consistent joke, but it was taken seriously. It's doubtless disgraceful, but it's the last he shall ever make. Forgive his weariness over his deadly backward book, which isn't a joke, unless he doesn't know the difference. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Violet Hunt, "Saturday" [1901 March 16], ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 4:16)
      Any day after the 25th will do. She will come back saturated with romance, and she will find James a sympathetic [devourer?] and he doesn't have any one of ces dames! #6251-o
    - Henry James to Violet Hunt, 1901 March 26, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 4:17)
      The man about town will with pleasure emerge from his club at 5 next Wednesday and join the woman about town at hers. The former is infinitely obliged to the latter. #6251-o
    - Henry James to Violet Hunt, [1901] March 29, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 4:18)
      Just got back and found the offering of her latest creation from her hand. Will give his attention to things she specifies. Touched by her remembering their brief talk, which brings back one of his London hours of crowded life with piercing intensity; he is faced with a great lonely horizon. Human interest is lacking, and he eagerly turns to her confidently. #6251-o
    - Henry James to Violet Hunt, 1901 April 28, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 4:19)
      Her note reached him, but he has been ill in bed with a bad throat, so now he sits face to face with pile of responsibilities. Gives the coming months in town a wide berth and is in retreat. But her poor little Corker, what is one to say? #6251-o
    - Henry James to Hendrik [Christian Anderson] 1901 May 4, ALS, 8 pp. on 4 l. (Box-folder 4:20)
      What an arch brute he must think of James for failing to thank him for photographs. Spent four months in London. Brother, wife, and children are visiting and taking all his time. They found Hans delightful in Rome. A lot about his Lincoln and traveling all over Italy. Discusses various parts of Lincoln and his approval. A seated Lincoln shocks him for he always stood tall. Suggests improvements. He is more placid than one's own image and memory. Benevolent, deeply troubled, altogether tragic. Forgive criticism. #6251
    - Henry James to Theodora [Sedgwick], [1901] June 5, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 4:21)
      Rejoices in her news that poor E.L.G. is here. Wrote to them. When they try to get into real residence, the tug of war will come. Tugs to extract pleasure that the brave impression of England these lovely days must be giving him. #6251-e
    - Henry James to Miss Grace Carter, 1901 June 9, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. with envelope and typed transcript. (Box-folder 4:22)
      Welcomes news she has returned. Ill since news arrived. Now ready to meet her. No travel this year. The Mermaid flourishes and welcomes her and her niece. #6251-ac
    - Henry James to Miss Grace Carter, [1901 June 15], ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. with envelope and typed transcript. (Box-folder 4:23)
      Glad she is arranging to come. Sorry he has planned other company. There will be a congested scene of action, but he will nip around to The Mermaid at the slightest respite. #6251-ac
    - Henry James to Miss Grace Carter, [1901 June 21], ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. with envelope and typed transcript. (Box-folder 4:24)
      Received missives and will do justice to her hospitality, scruples, and fears. But it would be better to dine with James briefly and simply at 7 sharp. Will be able to make it to the opera more efficiently. #6251-ac
    - Henry James to Miss Grace Carter, [1901 June 26], ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope and typed transcript. (Box-folder 4:25)
      Thanks her for offer of a truly operatic privilege, but hindered and hampered his impulse. She is generous and gallant beyond compare, but he presently has three relations in the house and must remain home. Fondly recollects past operatic experience. #6251-ac
    - Henry James to Grace Carter, "Thursday p.m." [1901 June?], ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with typed transcript. (Box-folder 4:26)
      Asks that Grace and Miss Brown dine with him on Saturday before the opera. La Tosca begins at 8, so call dinner at 7. Will meet at the Grosvenor Club. #6251-ac
    - Henry James to Hendrik [Christian Anderson] 1901 July 1, ALS, 8 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 4:27)
      More shocked and grieved than he can say with his whole winter's work and high hopes and good faith. Worried since he hadn't heard since he received photographs. Asks him to come to England until he is consoled and cheered. Must leave Italy. Can give him a studio. In Rome the sculptor works for a great vulgar, stupid community that revels in vulgarity and only quakes at the blessed nude. #6251
    - Henry James to Mrs. Robinson, 1901 August 13, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 4:28)
      How can he express an answer to her kind note as he is in bondage to his confirmed habit of never dining out in the country, so he cannot accept her invitation. He will come over some afternoon and explain everything. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Hendrik [Christian Anderson], 1901 September 13, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 4:29)
      His letter was a joy. Wants him to come soon. Shall try to stretch out his promised work. Will talk of blessed good news he brings from Rome. Come the first moment he can. #6251
    - Henry James to [Hendrik Christian Anderson], 1901 September 17, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 4:30)
      Sooner he sees him the better and gives train schedule. Bear up through his ill-seen London, in his dreary condition. #6251
    - Henry James to [Hendrik Christian Anderson], 1901 October 5, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 4:31)
      Thanks for his signal of safety after woeful journey. Likes to think of him fixed for the Roman winter and wishes him high tide of inspirational and execution, to float him over every worry and land him in peace and renown. Misses him out of all proportion to the too few hours he was there. Tell him if more occurs to him regarding Norway business. Can't bear not to know his nightmares. #6251
    - Henry James to [Sir George] Henschel, 1901 December 6, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 4:32)
      Touched by his having found time to express anything in respect to his ineffectual participation. Please remember he continues to think of him with considerable power of evocation. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Violet Hunt, 1902 January 8, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 4:33)
      Embarrassed to advise her. He did give Ortmann a thing for his A.A. Magazine (not Review) because he had published 2 longish things of his in Cosmopolitan and paid decently well. Ortman has been in dire straits since Cosmopolitan collapsed; doesn't see why she must provide Ortman with the table of contents for nothing. James will send his copy of new magazine when he gets it for her to judge. Will come up within a month. Ask James to tea at her little white club. #6251-o
    - Henry James to Hendrik [Christian Anderson], 1902 February 9, ALS, 10 pp. on 3 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 4:34)
      His news fills him with horror and pity. His heart bleeds at vision of him alone in wicked and indifferent Rome with this haunting and unbearable sorrow. Aches to know he can't be there to hold him, etc. What a dismal winter, with the staggering blow at the climax. Hopes he may come to England for consolation. Embraces him with a passion of pity. #6251
    - Henry James to Violet Hunt, 1902 February 27, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. with 35 mm. negative. (Box-folder 4:35)
      Often thought of her for month when he was ill and unable to write feeling helpless and hopeless. At last he is better and crawling out of his deep hole. Only saved his life by scrambling back there. This is his first non-wired communication with the world. He has the terror of convalescence awaiting him. Sends her The Story in Italy. Will she return? Always suspected Cosmopolitan Seraglio. #6251-o
    - Henry James to [Hendrik Christian Anderson], 1902 February 28, ALS, 8 pp. on 4 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 4:36)
      Too ill to write sooner in London, but now convalescent at home. Didn't want to cruelly worry him. Now James' weak arms can fold Anderson close. Has gone through death to death in his long life, to know how all that we are and have, all that is best within us, our genius, our imagination, our passion become opens gates to suffering, to being flooded. James tells Anderson, "Let yourself go and live now as a lacerated mutilated lover, with your grief, your loss, your sore unforgettable consciousness." Possess them and let them possess you and life will still hold you in her arms. Beautiful and unspeakable Anderson's account of his relation to Andreas: sacred beyond tears. James wishes he had known Andreas, an admirable, loveable boy. Andreas is all Anderson's now: With Anderson's patience, genius and courage, things will come back to him. #6251
    - Henry James to [Hendrik Christian Anderson], [1902] March 19, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 4:37)
      Can't leave Anderson's last letter without saying how touched he is to the heart, with his tenderest, healing benediction. Anderson mustn't waste another thought on any trouble of James's. James is blessedly better, and only wanting to go back to work. #6251
    - Henry James to Violet Hunt, 1902 June 17, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 4:38)
      Newspapers lie a great deal, but prompted her to write. Thinks James is working through nightmare. His book delayed, but will be out soon, and will send her a copy. Shall seek her out at earliest occasion after pandemonium of the present has subsided. Thanks her for her circular account of Monna Vanna which he shall not see enacted. Shall read with disappointment. James loves Maeterlinck: a beautiful mind. Strikes him as treated with strange heaviness, as if to make up for rare temerity of his old beautiful things. But he blasphemes. Wished he could go to a performance with her. #6251-o
    - Henry James to Hendrik [Christian Anderson], 1902 August 13, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 4:39)
      Blow to learn Anderson is passing by so near James and not stopping. Waiting for Anderson's September visit. Natural that Anderson should be making for Paris. With Anderson's mother and brother he can work in as few complications as possible. James wishes he might have seen them, too. Wishes he could say he could get to Italy this winter. Yearns to go for a long stay and pick Anderson up and take him to places he wants to see. Would like to hear about Anderson's time in America. Hopes he has been able to put something solid under his feet and something bright before his eyes. He must march to glory with lengthening strides. May his mother find comfort in being with him and helped by him. #6251
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Humphrey] Ward, 1902 September 23, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 4:40)
      Thanks for her generous letter. Thinks he sees faults of his too voluminous fiction. When a thing is done, he sees nothing but the faults: three or four major ones. None are the objection she raises. Agrees subject is a poor one. The thing is essentially a drama, like everything he does. Can't come to her as not possible to leave home. In town January to May. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Violet Hunt, 1902 November 5, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope; with typed transcript by Violet Hunt (Box-folder 4:41)
      Fat fearful book went to her with blushing compunction, but he does not come to town until after Christmas. Sorry he failed to send her The Wings of the Dove, but he lost his head. Hopes her brave life is winning most of its battles. Glad she is seeing Constance Fletcher. Shall have her autograph at earliest opportunity. #6251-o
    - Henry James to [William Morton?] Fullerton, 1902 November 7, ALS, 6 pp. on 3 l. (Box-folder 4:42)